Guide to the Michael Padwee Papers WAG.004
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Michael Padwee Papers
1966-1979
WAG.004
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
4.0 linear feet (4 boxes)
Michael Padwee was a caseworker for the New York City Department of Social Services, Human Resources Administration and a member of the Social Service Employees Union (SSEU, AFSCME District Council 37, Local 371). While a member of the union, he served as a union delegate and grievance committee chairman and was an active member of several union caucuses. Beginning in his student days at Rutgers University, Padwee was active in several leftist and activist organizations. He was a founding member of Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) and Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) chapters at Rutgers. After college, he became active in the New American Movement (NAM) and the Movement for a Democratic Society. This collection contains material documenting his involvement with various political organizations and unions, and it includes material authored by Michael Padwee for SSEU caucuses and for NAM. NOTE: This collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Padwee, Michael
Provenance
The papers of Michael Padwee were donated to the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by Mr. Padwee in October 1979.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. NOTE: This collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Historical/Biographical Note
Michael Wayne Padwee was born on December 4, 1942 in Jersey City, New Jersey. He graduated from Weehawken High School in 1960, and received a B.S. in Chemistry from Rutgers University in 1964, an M.A. in History from Rutgers in 1966, an M.L.S. from Queens College in 1975, and an M.S.W. from Columbia University in 1982.
A long-time political activist, Michael Padwee was a founding member of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE) chapter at Rutgers University, starting in 1963. He was arrested with civil rights leader James Farmer when the Rutgers Chapter joined in picketing the 1964 World's Fair in New York. Padwee went on to form a chapter of Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) at Rutgers. As a member of SDS, he helped sponsor a series of "teach-ins" at the University, including a controversial speech by alleged Communist, and then Rutgers professor, Eugene Genovese. He also organized a number of protests and helped set up Community Action Projects in the New Brunswick Community. In late 1971, Padwee became active in the New American Movement (NAM). He participated as a voting delegate at the founding convention of NAM and went on to help form a NAM chapter in New York City, where he served as Secretary. He also participated in the city-wide Committee for Independent Political Action (CIPA), which was involved in campaigns of third-party candidates, including James Weinstein's campaign as an independent socialist for the Congressional seat in the 19th District.
Padwee began working at the New York City Department of Social Services, Human Resources Administration, as a caseworker in the summer of 1966, when he was assigned to the Veterans' Welfare Center. Almost immediately he joined the Social Service Employees Union (SSEU); the union, now SSEU, AFSCME DC 37, Local 371, was then independent, formed when caseworkers split from Local 371 in 1962. In early 1967, Mr. Padwee was elected as an alternate delegate in the union and began distributing his own newsletter, Dishonorable Discharge, at the Veterans' Welfare Center. In the spring of 1968, he ran unsuccessfully for a delegate position in the union. Shortly thereafter he became a co-grievance chairman for the Center. While at the Veterans' Center, Mr. Padwee was active in a number of union caucuses and subgroups including Welfare Workers for Peace, Rank and File Committee, "Coalition," Members for Militant and Democratic Unionism, and the Welfare Chapter of the Movement for a Democratic Society. In 1968-69 when a spirited debate went on within the local union over whether to re-affiliate with DC37, Padwee was active in the Anti-Merger Caucus. The SSEU fought for higher wages and better working conditions, but was also seen by much of its membership as a vehicle for affecting wider social and political issues such as child welfare, homelessness, the AIDS crisis, anti-Apartheid and civil rights struggles and the movement against the Vietnam War. The union caucus Welfare Workers for Peace, won the support of the local for anti-war demonstrations and organized members to pass an anti-war resolution that was drafted by Padwee. The SSEU became the first union in the country to vote by referendum to call on the U.S. to withdraw from Vietnam.
Throughout the 1968 and 1969 struggles within the SSEU over re-affiliation with District Council 37 Padwee was deeply involved in organizing an opposition to re-affiliation. When the issue was resolved by a pro-merger vote of the membership, his workplace, the Veterans' Welfare Center, was one of only four centers to vote against the measure. Padwee resigned from the union for a short time, but returned in May of 1969, when he transferred to the Bureau of Child Welfare Division of Homefinding. He left the Welfare Department in November of 1969 to move to Baltimore, and returned to NYC and was rehired by the Division of Homefinding in April of 1970.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Political Activity, 1963-1974.
Series I includes documents illustrating Padwee's involvement in various leftist political groups including Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), the Socialist Scholars Conference, the Movement for a Democratic Society (MDS), the Peace and Freedom Party (PFP), the Committee for Independent Political Action (CIPA), Red Umbrella, and the New American Movement (NAM). Included in this series are position papers, minutes, flyers, pamphlets, notes, clippings, newsletters, publications and correspondence from the various organizations. Highlights include materials written by Michael Padwee for NAM.
Series II: Social Service Employees Union, 1966-1973.
Series II includes minutes, notes, flyers, pamphlets, and position papers related to union activities and dissident groups within the union. The series covers union politics, particularly the dispute surrounding the proposed merger of the SSEU with Local 371 of DC 37, AFSCME in 1969. Highlights include materials written by Michael Padwee for the Veterans' Welfare Center and various caucuses within the SSEU and materials relating to the SSEU's stance against the Vietnam War.
NOTE: This collection is stored offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by topic within each series.
The files are grouped into two series:
I, Political Activity
II, Social Service Employees Union
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Social Service Employees Union Records (AFSCME DC 37, Local 371) (Wagner # 3)
Sol Gorelick Papers (Wagner #19)
Christopher Dykema Papers (Wagner #16)
Black Panther Party.; Coalition for Jobs and Services (New York, N.Y.).; Committee for Independent Political Action (New York, N.Y.).; Congress of Racial Equality.; Dykema, Christopher; Genovese, Eugene D., 1930-; Movement for a Democratic Society.; New American Movement (Organization).; Red Umbrella (Organization).; Resistance (Organization: U.S.).; Social Service Employees Union. Local 371.; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.).; Civil rights workers |z United States.; Correspondence.; Fliers (printed matter); Memoirs.; Minutes.; New Brunswick (N.J.); New York (N.Y.); Newsletters.; Pamphlets.; Publications.; Reports.; Student movements |z New Jersey.; Student movements |z New York (State) |z New York.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 |x Protest movements.; White collar workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Series I: Political Activity
  - Autobiographical Manuscript, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Center for Independent Revolutionary Socialists, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Committee for Free Speech, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Committee for Independent Political Action (CIPA): 19 Newsletter (19th Congressional District), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - CIPA: Mailings, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CIPA: Organizational Material, undated, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - CIPA: Weinstein Campaign, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Common Sense: An Independent Student Newsletter, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7A)
  - CORE: Baez, Joan, Concert for CAP (Community Action Project), Jul 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - CORE: Capsule Newsletter, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - CORE: Demonstration against Governor Ross Barnett, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - CORE: Fast for Freedom, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - CORE: Harris, Don, Imprisonment, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - CORE: New Brunswick Project, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - CORE: New York World's Fair Picket, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - CORE: Organizational Material, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - CORE: Strom Thurmond Protest, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - End the Draft, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 16a)
  - GI Contact Committee, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hawker (Monmouth College radical newsletter), 1967 (?) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Independent Socialist Club, undated, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Movement for a Democratic Society (MDS): The Big Us, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - MDS Coordinating Committee, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - MDS: Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - MDS: Mouthpiece, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - MDS: Organizational Material, undated, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - MDS: Pamphlets and Leaflets, undated, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - MDS: Position Papers, undated, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - National Caucus of Labor Committees, undated, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - National Federation of Social Service Employees, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - New American Movement (NAM): Bulletin, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - NAM: Campaign '73, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - NAM: Conference Davenport, Iowa, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - NAM: Correspondence, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - NAM: Correspondence, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - NAM: Debate between Michael Padwee andChris Dykema, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - NAM: Economic Task Force, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - NAM: Farm Workers Strike, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - NAM: Founding Convention, Minneapolis, MN, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - NAM: Impeach Nixon Campaign, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - NAM: Farah Strike, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - NAM: National Council, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - NAM: National Interim Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - NAM: National Office, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - NAM: New York City Chapters, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - NAM: Newsletters, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - NAM: North County Peace Campaign, undated, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - NAM: "Occasional Report", 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - NAM: Pamphlets and Leaflets, undated, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - NAM: Position Papers, undated, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - NAM: Radical Teachers' Conference, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - NAM: Regional Conference, Amherst, MA, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - NAM: Second Convention, Dekalb, IL, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - NAM: Socialism and Feminism Conference, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - NAM: Telephone Workers Strike, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - NAM: War and Imperialism Task Force, undated, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - NAM: Welfare Forced Labor Committee, undated, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - NAM: Workplace Conference, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - NAM: Workplace Newsletter Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - New Jersey Correspondent, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Peace and Freedom Party (PFP): Black Panther Party, undated, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - PFP: Cleaver, Eldridge, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - PFP: Minutes, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - PFP: Organizational Materials, undated, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - PFP: Pamphlets and Leaflets, undated, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - PFP: Peace and Freedom News and Peace and Freedom Organizer, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - People against Racism, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Power Thru Unity Collective (NYC students), 1970 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Public Employees against War, Repression and Exploitation, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Professionals for Change, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Rank and File Publications; AFSCME, Transport Workers Union, Communications Workers of America, etc.), 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Raritan Peace News, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Red and the Black (Rutgers University), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Red Umbrella (NYC socialist groups), 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Resistance, The, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - SANE (National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy), 1963-1968 (Box 3, Folder 2a)
  - Students for a Democratic Society (SDS): Anti-Vietnam War Activities, 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - SDS: Aptheker, Herbert, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - SDS: AVANTI! Newsletter, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - SDS: Chicago Protest, Oct 1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - SDS Correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - SDS: Daily Home News Letters to the Editor, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - SDS: Dumont/Genovese Debate, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - SDS: Free the Panther 21, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - SDS: Genovese, Eugene, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - SDS: GRANPA, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - SDS: Labor Committee, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - SDS: March on Washington, Apr 1965 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - SDS: March on Washington, Nov 1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - SDS: National Convention, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - SDS: Newsletters, ca.1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - SDS: Open Admissions, undated, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - SDS: Opposition to the Draft, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - SDS: Organizational Material, 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - SDS: Pamphlets and Leaflets, undated, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - SDS: The Participant, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - SDS: Position Papers, undated, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - SDS: Press Articles, 1965-1977 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - SDS: Radical Education Project, undated, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - SDS: Revolutionary Youth Movement II, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - SDS: Targum Letters to the Editor, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - SDS: Teach-Ins, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - SDS: Worker-Student Alliance, 1969-1972 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - SDS Worklist, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Socialist Scholars Conference, 1965-1970 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Social Welfare Workers Movement, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Student Non-Violent Coordinating Committee, 1961-1966 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Trade Unionists for a Labor Party, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - West Side Tenants Union, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Workers Action Movement, undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Series II: Social Service Employees Union.
  - Activist List, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Bargaining, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Bureau of Child Welfare, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Bargaining: Conference, Jan 1973 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Bargaining: Proposals, 1964-1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Coalition (SSEU caucus), 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Committee for New Leadership, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Committee Reports, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Community Action Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Contract Demands, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Delegate Assembly, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Delegate Elections, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Department of Social Services, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Department of Welfare, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Division of Homefinding, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Draft Counseling Service, 1969-1970 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Grievance (Brecker, et al.), 1973 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Human Resources Administration, Department of Social Services, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Human Resources Administration, City of New York, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Independent Workers Committee, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Jurisdiction List, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Local 371 Organizational Newsletter, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Member Lists, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Members for a Militant Caucus, 1966-1971 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Members for Militant and Democratic Unionism, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Membership Meeting Minutes and Handouts, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Militant Workers' Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Movement for a Democratic Society, Welfare Chapter, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Movement for Progressive Unionism, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Newsletters, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1966-1973 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Organizing Material, Mar 1968 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Pamphlets, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Petitions, 1967-1973 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Position Papers, 1965-1968 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Progressive Labor Party, 1968 (?)-1969 (?) (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Proposed Constitution, 1968 (?) (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Public Employees for Militant Unionism, 1967 (?) (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Rank and File Committee, 1966-1972 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - SSEU Local 371, AFSCME: Proposed Merger Agreement, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - SSEU Members for the SSEU, 1968-1969 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Strike Committee, Undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Supervisors Chapter; Organizer's Guide, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Veterans Welfare Center, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Welfare Fund, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Welfare Workers for Peace, 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 49)